hello everybody my name is Jennifer
maker today we are learning how to make
personalized t-shirts with our crickets
and iron-on vinyl on the great maker
show and towel so one of the reasons
that many people buy a cricket in the
first place is to be able to make
awesome personalized t-shirts like this
one and it's really easy to see why the
cricket is perfect for t-shirt making
and it cuts out iron-on vinyl designs
like a champ a couple of months ago I
did a full color print and then cut
tutorial for t-shirts and it was a big
hit but printing cut can be a little
challenging for beginners so I wanted to
dial things back a bit and do a very
easy tutorial on how to make a t-shirt
using iron-on vinyl with a Cricut so for
this project we're going to be working
with iron and vinyl also known as heat
transfer vinyl or HTV and this is a
special vinyl that has a heat sensitive
adhesive that will stick to fabric and
other surfaces when pressed down with a
heat source like a household iron or an
easy press and I will show you how to do
both in this tutorial now the cool thing
about the Cricut is that you can cut out
a design or a name or really whatever
you want from iron and vinyl using lots
of different colors and textures and
designs like this foil and if you do it
right
your shirt can be washed up to 50 times
before you start to have any issues and
I'm going to show you the right way to
do it in this video so that you get
great results on your first try now
because the thing is there's really a
bunch of things that can go wrong when
you're making an iron-on t-shirt you
need to remember to mirror it or flip
the design you might you have to put the
vinyl on your cutting mat with the
right-side up you have to weed the right
part out of your design pre-heat your
shirt set your temperature to the right
amount press it long enough and remove
the carrier sheet at the right time the
good news is that I'm going to be right
here with you the whole time
by your side making sure that you're
able to do this right so let's start
with materials that you're going to need
and then I'm going to show you how to
prepare a t-shirt design for cutting on
your Cricut so here's everything that
I'll be using in this tutorial to make a
simple basic iron-on t-shirt we're going
to use 100% cotton t-shirts
I bought these from both Michaels and
Joanne's I believe they're Gildan brand
and I will link to those in this
tutorial now there are some debate as to
whether you need to pre wash or not
Cricut recommends that you pre wash and
thus I have pre washed these some people
feel that it's not necessary especially
because it doesn't look quite as good if
you intend to sell them one thing that
is very important however is that they
are preshrunk which this brand is by the
way so it's up to you whether you want
to pre wash it or not we're also going
to need some vinyl I'm going to use
Cricut vinyl for this tutorial and we're
going to use virtually every kind of
Cricut vinyl that I can find so that you
can see the different styles and how it
looks and how it works to actually apply
it to the shirt you also need a way to
cut out your vinyl and we're going to
use a Cricut and all you need for that
is a Cricut Explorer or a Cricut maker
and a regular fine point blade that's
all that's necessary you also want to
the standard grip mat that's the green
matte right here as far as tools go I'm
going to use a weeding tool and a
tweezers can come in very helpful from
when you're weeding
I also recommend a pair of scissors or a
craft knife so that you can cut your
vinyl off of the roll easily and I like
to use a brayer so I can adhere my vinyl
down to my mat so everything is nice and
smooth and to apply the vinyl to your
shirt you're going to want to use an
easy press or a household iron or if you
have a heat press I don't have a heat
press so I won't be showing you that in
this video but I will show you how to
use the easy press and a regular iron to
iron with you're also going to need a
surface to iron on not an ironing board
I'll be using an easy press mat to do
that all right so let's head on over
- Cricut design space so I can show you
how to prepare your design so here we
are in Cricut design space and we want
to start by clicking on new project and
I recommend that you use templates which
you which is accessible if you're on the
desktop version of Cricut design space
and I think it's just really helpful for
determining the size if you have a
template so I'm gonna go ahead and use
the classic t-shirt template and I'm
gonna turn off the grid just so we can
see that so woman's short-sleeve medium
t-shirt and we'll even change the color
since we're going since I'm gonna start
with a yellow t-shirt but this part
doesn't matter this is just for
designing so here we have a yellow shirt
and we need a design for this now
there's tons of awesome designs in
Cricut design space just click on images
and you can search through various
things you know ask me about my beard
never stop looking up these are all
awesome designs very cute there's a
Cricut QT but I've created a design that
I want to use for this project so I'm
going to upload that and you're all
welcome to use this design free as well
so if you go to my blog at
jennifermcguireink.com today the
password now I have everything organized
in here and we're looking for the craft
heart SVG file I'm going to go ahead and
download that and we're going to open
that up and there we go we have that
right there okay now we go back to
cookie design space and click on upload
then upload image and then browse and
we're going to go find into our
downloads folder
we're gonna go find that craft heart
jennipher maker directory and you may
have to unzip it and we're gonna go
ahead and upload the SVG file and if
you're not familiar with how to use SVG
s I have a whole training series on that
that will walk you through it
step-by-step
jennipher maker.com / SVG's all right so
I've uploaded this and I'll go ahead and
save it to my image library and then I'm
going to select it here and then click
insert images and it's gonna show up on
my canvas and I've already sized this to
look great on a t-shirt now you'll
notice that I have the design here which
is a winged heart and it says craft in
the middle and then I had this little
heart down here in the corner now this
heart is here for testing purposes if
you don't want to test you can go ahead
and hide it over here with the eye icon
let's just like that but I really like
to test before I you know make a mistake
on a t-shirt I like to make sure that my
iron on vinyl works well and I have my
settings properly set before I go ahead
and put it in a shirt and I highly
recommend you do that too so if you'd
like to test I recommend that you go
ahead and cut out this heart you're not
going to keep that heart there what
we're going to do is move this heart
down probably to the corner here like
this but it's not necessary to do that
right now you can do that later when
you're doing your testing but if this is
the design if you want to change
anything about it you certainly can
right now I have it set to red and which
I'm going to do one of my designs in red
let me zoom a little bit down here with
the buttons in the lower left corner now
I want to note one thing here which is
if for any reason you don't want the
name Jennifer maker to show up on your
shirt which is fine I won't be offended
you can totally do that if you click on
the the design and then click on contour
over here you can actually select each
one of these little hearts I'm sorry
each one of these little letters and you
can see them here as well if you select
them they will actually be removed from
your the design itself so we can get rid
of all of these letters or anything else
in the design you that you might not
want for example perhaps you don't want
the little shine here so you could get
rid of that as well perhaps you don't
want it to be outlines like you know the
wings outline so you could actually
remove that as
and it would look like this okay but if
you do want those things which I do
you're going to want to go ahead and
show everything so that's what I've got
there all right so everything is here
and it's all ready to go of course we
can double check that our design looks
the way we want
you know this design is 7.99
it's basically eight inches wide which i
think is a really good size for an adult
the t-shirt you can make it bigger if
you like you can make it smaller it's up
to you but I have sizes to look good on
a t-shirt but you can use this template
to determine what might look good right
so for example this which is we could
cut this out on the Cricut is probably
no it's definitely too big because
remember this people are 3d right and
this would start to wrap around the body
if it was this big so I think that
generally speaking eight inches is
actually a really good size for a
t-shirt so there is our design all ready
to go
and it's time to make it so we click the
make it button in the upper right hand
corner right here just like this now
there's something very important that we
must do for iron on vinyl and we must
mirror our images and this is true for
all iron on vinyl that I've ever worked
with you have to when you cut the iron
on vinyl you actually cut it upside down
and that means that we need to mirror it
which means to cut it you know like the
design flipped as if it we were looking
at it in a mirror it's very easy to do
and Cricut design space over here on the
left it says mirror and you just toggle
this so it becomes green and it flips
around just like this and I also suggest
that you take that extra little heart
that you're going to test with and move
it over um so there's just a little bit
more space so just over here like this
you just click and drag that and then we
click continue
and then you'll want to connect your
machine if you have more than one like I
do and if not it will show up here
automatically I'm going to connect my
Cricut explore air too you can of course
use a maker for this as well if you're
using a Cricut Explorer like I am I
recommend that
you set your dial to custom that will
allow you to fine-tune your materials in
Cricut design space I actually always
leave my dial on custom and then we need
to choose our materials so for the very
first I turn on vinyl shirt that I've
been doing in this video we're going to
use Cricut everyday iron-on so I'm just
gonna search for every day and there it
is I'm gonna select that and click done
and I like to switch my my pressure to
more it's just something that works well
for me so we've got it set to everyday
iron-on and we have it set to more now
there's a little note here that says
make sure mayor is turned on and I run
material is placed shiny side down and
now we'll go over that later in this
video but make sure that this mirror
over here says mirror on it's very
important all right so we're ready to
cut this let's go ahead and talk about
how to determine which side of the
iron-on vinyl to cut all right so it's
time to cut out our non vinyl
we're going to use the standard grip mat
and for our first t-shirt we're going to
use Cricut everyday iron-on vinyl which
I've already opened so that makes it a
little bit easier I'll just slide that
right off now my design is will use the
full length and it's four inches and you
can always check that in Cricut design
space if you don't recall so how much
vinyl to cut off you can just use
scissors or you can use a craft knife to
just cut it off which I will do right
now
it's approximately four inches right
there you can of course be more exact if
you'd like
go
tape that back up and don't forget to
put your unit back on the tape it or
slide it in the bottom so that you don't
forget what kind of vinyl you used all
right so now this little a tricky part
which is which side of the vinyl to put
down I've created an entire video to
help you identify which is the side to
cut on your vinyl the easy rule to
remember is shiny side down okay so
we're going to go ahead and put sunny
side down there are some exceptions and
that happens when it's shiny on both
sides and it's hard to tell which side
and my video explains exactly what to do
if that's not in the right spot my video
shows you exactly what to do and how to
determine the right side to cut your
iron on vinyl every time so that you
don't waste any materials I like to use
my brayer to make sure that the vinyl is
really well adhered to the mat so
there's no wrinkles you don't want any
wrinkles when you cut this all right
there we go that's all set now our next
step is to cut this out so we've already
prepared it in design space and sent it
to our Cricut so we're going to go ahead
and cut it now now you want to make sure
that you have your fine point blade in
and that everything is all good to go
and you want to watch for the flashing
Cricut button and when that's ready to
go you go ahead and you press the button
and it starts to cut
all right there we go and once it's cut
we unload our machine with unload button
and we have our material all cut out
note that you can see that but it's
definitely cut out and that looks
excellent
so we peel it off our mat Thomas is
easier to place it facedown and that
look that I like to tuck my mats under
my machine so they're out of the way
just like that alright and then we are
left with our design which we can see
here this is going to be the top of it
and this is covered with the carrier
sheet it's stuck to it already so you
don't need to have any kind of transfer
tape or anything it's actually pretty
awesome in that way but what we do need
to do now is weed our project so weeding
means to remove all of the vinyl that we
don't want transferred to our project
when we iron it on or use a heat press
so that means we remove all the extra
little bits and you're going to want a
winning tool for this and I also use my
craft knife because I'd like to get it
started because it's I find it very
difficult to just sort of peel it away
from the edge
it never really wants to come free very
easily so what I do is make a small Nick
in the corner you don't want to cut all
the way through just cut through the
iron-on final and I'm on the mat side
the cut side right now and then it's
easier to peel off once you've made that
cut I find so I have just nicked the
corner right here and now I can get my
fingernail under the edge of the vinyl
easier because of that little nick if
you have any problems you can use your
weeding tool to kind of pull it away
like this there we go and once you have
it started you just continue to pull it
away from the carrier sheet and your
design will stay on the carrier sheet
and
part that you do not want will pull away
just like this there we go now if you
look at it you'll see that there are not
all of it has been removed right so
we've got the parts inside the heart and
the wings and the letters as well let's
go ahead and cut this off right here and
we'll save this heart for our test and
always keep your little scraps in off to
the side away from your work area so
that they don't get mixed in with other
things all right so here's our heart and
I said that there now
the design has hollow wings so we will
just use the winning tool to just sort
of scrape it away that's all I do and
then I usually pull it away with my
fingers once I've got a good grip on it
it's not a difficult project to weed the
trickiest part is the letters I did
intentionally put easy things and hard
things in this design because if you're
beginner and trying to learn it's
helpful to have both and that if it
turns out that you can't get these
letters weighted very well you could
always just cut them out right worse
comes to worse all right so we need to
get the top of the heart here
and there's stuff keep our bits of vinyl
off to the side and the bottom and then
we also have you know we usually hold
this up to the light to see which parts
you need you can of course use a light
box but I am not using one today but
always these little bits if they get
stuck anywhere on your PLAs you know the
carrier sheet they might get transferred
to your t-shirt to always keep those off
of your work surface as you are weeding
[Music]
comes away from the tee as well and
there's a section between the F and the
tee and the bottom of the F
there we go
now as I said these letters are going to
be the trickiest part down here where it
says Jennifer maker
it's definitely trickiest part we just
be patient and if you need to you can
use your tweezers to get the little bits
off without hurting the letters all
right there we have we did our hole
design
and that's what it looks like and this
is how it'll pair when you put it on our
shirt so now it's time to apply our iron
iron design onto our t-shirt I'm gonna
start with the easy press because I
think many people have it and it's
really I really think it's quite a bit
superior to an iron and that makes it a
little easier to do so we're gonna do a
test with the easy press we're going to
make sure that this heart applies and
the carrier sheet comes off and it looks
good using our setting this is our
Cricut pressing mat and we're going to
use the yellow shirt all right so I'm
gonna put I'm gonna put this heart right
here in the corner just like this so
that we can test it and make sure that
our settings are good of course now we
need to figure out what the right
settings are so there is a whole
interactive calculator online the Cricut
easy press interactive a quick reference
guide will tell you exactly what
temperature and how long to preheat and
how much pressure and what everything
that you need to do to get excellent
results without having to guess at it I
still like to do the test though because
I mean t-shirts aren't inexpensive
alright so here we go so we're going to
use everyday iron-on is our material and
our base material is 100% cotton and we
are using a Cricut easy press mat and
this now tells us exactly what we need
to use for our project so it wants us to
pre wash the item when
have again without fabric softener set
the temperature to 315 degrees preheat
for five seconds apply heat and gentle
pressure for 30 seconds
flip the material over and press for 15
seconds peel off warm and of course you
know you need to allow 24 hours for
before you wash it all right so let's do
that alright so we're gonna turn on the
Cricut easy press with the power button
right there we want to set it to 315
degrees so we click we press the
thermometer button just once and then
push the plus sign until we're at 3:15
then press the thermometer button again
and we want 30 seconds which is already
set to but if you don't know how to do
that you press the stop watch button and
then you use the plus and minus signs to
adjust it to the proper length of time
and then you press the stop watch button
again so right now we have it set to 315
for 30 seconds which is going to be our
maximum press time so that's the right
time that we want to use and the
instructions call for preheating our
material and all that means is we're
going to take our easy press and we're
going to press it down on our material
for at least 5 seconds it can be a
little longer I don't think that part
really matters the idea is you want to
heat it up so that it removes moisture
it kind of also pre shrinks that t-shirt
as well and it gets it ready for the
iron-on vinyl application so that's
pretty important now you do want to wait
until your Cricut easy process that's on
the right temperature but what I love
about this is that we can say a specific
temperature which we can't do with our
iron and it'll also time it for us and
it's got all also has this really
excellent flat surface that makes it so
much easier to use and this by the way
it's the smallest Cricut ez press and
they there are two other sizes but this
project just is fine with the smaller
size all right so we're all ready to go
we're at 315 we have our timers
thirty Seconds we're going to start by
preheating our surface for five seconds
you can press this button and they'll
count down five seconds if you don't
want to just guess at it alright it's
five seconds alright so now we want to
place our heart our test in the corner
just like this right now we're placing
it kind of there's a sticky sides the
carrier sheet and a non sticky side you
pray pressing this sticky side down just
like this and make sure there's no other
little bits of anything little you know
parts that you weed it or anything like
that
make sure your Cricut ez press says the
right temperature and number of seconds
again and then we're going to place it
on our mat and we're going to press the
green button this starts the timer and
you want to give it gentle pressure that
means that you don't give you no lean
into it you don't compress your mat
you're just giving it a gentle pressure
so I'm just gently pushing down right
now on my on my t-shirt there should be
some pressure but it shouldn't be you
know firm pressure or anything like that
just gentle and we're going to wait
until we are a little our Cricut easy
press will beep when it's all finished
alright and now we need to flip it over
and press it again for 15 seconds same
temperature 15 seconds and there we go
so we can just watch the countdown on
the EZ press to make sure that we're
doing 15 seconds you don't need to move
it around like you might with an iron
you're just pressing them with gentle
pressure for this particular setting for
this shirt and this I'm dying on
material alright now our next step is to
peel off warm
that does not mean peel off hot because
right now it's very hot if you were just
press your finger on this you could even
burn your finger you want to wait a
little bit until it's warm to the touch
instead of hot to the touch so you know
that will depend a little bit you know
ten
fifteen seconds maybe 30 seconds I like
to lift up the corner see how it feels
does it feel too hot definitely too hot
when you press on it and it feels too
hot it's too hot so you just want to
give it a little time
don't confuse warm peel with hot peel
it's when a so the plastic is now warm
alright so now I would say it's warm
instead of hot so we're going to gently
peel off the carrier sheet just like
that and we have our heart let me give
you a closer look at this so here's a
closer look at what it looks like you
can see that it looks like it's pretty
well in here I don't see it pulling off
anywhere alright so we've determined
that so our heart looks good and our
easy press settings are good so we're
ready to actually create this shirt the
next step is to position our design so
it's centered on the shirt because if we
just guess we might not get it right a
little bit so I could totally just
eyeball this and say put it here what
you can do is use the tag at the top as
a center mark for the heart but there as
a center mark for your design but there
is a better way actually
I recommend that you take your shirts
and you fold it in half so match up your
sleeves like this and fold it in half
nice like this
and use your ez press or your iron to
just put a little little crease there
just a little bit right just a little
bit of one so that we could determine
the exact center and now when you open
it up you will see that you can see the
exact center of your shirt which is
right here right so now we know exactly
where the center is and smooth that out
so there's no wrinkles you can still
just barely see that I can maybe you
can't but I can definitely see the
crease now we use that crease to Center
our design I prepared this design with a
very easy way to see our Center which is
the center of the heart so this is a
great beginner piece know your next
thing that you might be wondering is
where on the shirt do you put it do you
put it in the exact middle of your shirt
so this would be about the exact middle
do you put it or how high up do you put
it so especially you know I really think
that it's best to put this up a little
higher so I like to put it in the upper
half of the shirt I think that looks a
lot better when you do it that way
especially on women so that we can see
the design and it doesn't get a hidden
or you know messed up or whatever
because of the shape of the body
he doesn't look weird so I definitely
think the design is going to look better
in the top half right and to determine
the top half of the document or the
shirt just fold that in half and then we
know that this is the half here and so
we just Center that and the top half so
as long as you get this centered about
right here this is going to be just
right right here this will look great so
we want to just kind of remember this
position because we need to preheat our
shirt before we apply our design
remember just like we did our heart
earlier so I set this down here and
we're going to use our easy press to
preheat the area for five seconds all
right
now we're going to place our design
right in the spot that we've identified
as being ideal it should be right here
and you can press it down slightly and
it'll kind of stick and won't stick a
lot but enough so that you can put your
design on and put you know place it here
and then do your the easy press okay so
now it's time to do the pressing for 30
seconds I'm gonna set this right on top
just like this and press the timer and
apply gentle pressure make sure you're a
whole design is covered let's see we're
just a little bit too far that's okay so
what I'm going to do then is we're gonna
do half of our design on one side and
then I will switch it to the other side
for the another 30 seconds since we're
using the smaller easy press and again
I'm using gentle pressure alright and
then I'm gonna slide it down and do the
other half just like this so I'm just
lighting it up right in the very center
so I know exactly where to do the other
half
and again just gentle pressure you don't
need to use firm pressure for this
project and it's important that you
don't it's no more heat and more
pressure is not the solution when you're
having issues usually the the the best
thing to do is to follow the directions
it's in the interactive guide for the
easy press alright so now we can flip
this over and do the other side for 15
seconds so for this end I can just move
it back and forth a little bit so it has
even heat across its design so we don't
do it twice I wouldn't want to do that
for the front though in case that we
slid the carrier sheet when we were
doing it but it works okay for the back
alright
so we turn this over and just like with
our test heart we want to wait until our
design is warm instead of hot it's very
important if you try to peel it when
it's hot it will attempt to peel the
vinyl off as well so it's important that
we wait until it's the right temperature
again I like to start by touching the
edges of the plastic until that feels
warm and then when it does I touch the
design itself just be careful you can
definitely burn yourself all your finger
when you're testing so be mindful that
it's still definitely hot right now
all right so now it's warm to the touch
instead of hot so now we're gonna gently
peel it up and it's like magic because
our pretty design stays on the shirt
without any you know weird peeling or
coming off or anything because we follow
the directions exactly as it told us to
and that's the key Cricut has already
done all of the research to determine
what's going to work best with the easy
press and the material that you're using
and also what you're pressing it on and
again I'm using the Cricut pressing
matte but if you don't have one you can
use a folded towel what you don't want
to use is an ironing board or something
like that that does not work so there is
our finished design doesn't that look
awesome that turned out great it's gonna
be amazing and that is really it alright
so what if you don't have an easy press
but you have an iron I'm going to show
you how that works as well I've already
cut out a design and I have my iron
turned on we're going to use the
backside of the yellow t-shirt to do the
second design using our iron now we're
going to do a test again just to be
absolutely sure now you need to set your
dial to the cotton setting
this is a cotton shirt and you have to
pre-heat your shirt for 10 to 15 seconds
that's important always to preheat and
post heat and you'll want to place your
weeded image line your site up onto the
preheated material and you want to apply
medium pressure with the iron for 25 to
30 seconds now you'll notice the bottom
of the iron and the easy press are
different and the heat is not as evenly
distributed on the iron and so you want
to get your iron positioned over the
center of your image your design as much
as you possibly can it really will make
a difference and you'll notice that it's
stuck to the plastic for a moment just
right there so I'm gonna get a piece of
parchment paper because I don't trust my
iron to not be hurt by that plastic I
don't know why I did that we're just
gonna get some parchment paper and then
we don't have to worry about it and this
is just plain old household parchment
paper
nothing special besides that so here we
go I'm just gonna lay that parchment
paper right over my design just to
protect the surface of my iron and then
we're going to want to apply medium
pressure for 25 to 30 seconds again
we're trying to position the iron right
over the image as much as we possibly
can
and we're done when I flip that our
shirt over and again we're going to
apply medium pressure with iron to the
back of material for an extra 25 to 30
seconds and just like before you want to
peel it off warm not hot
when it feels good go ahead and peel off
the carrier sheet and there you go it
looks the same as the one that I did
with my ez press all right so now it's
all so now that we done our test and it
worked okay we're going to put our
design on the back of this shirt now
it's a little trickier because we
already have our design on the front and
this is where this ez press
mat comes in so handy because I can put
it right inside the shirt it's the
perfect size for it and it fits right in
there and we don't have to worry about
harming our original vinyl design it's
probably fine but hey why take chances
and I'm going to use the tag on the back
of the shirt to identify the center of
it just like before we need to preheat
our material for ten to fifteen seconds
and then we place our design with a
carrier sheet up liner up onto our shirt
and press it down so it's in place and
we're going to put that piece of
parchment on there again just to be on
the safe side I'd rather like this iron
I don't want to ruin it and we're going
to cover our design and apply medium
pressure for twenty-five to thirty
seconds and the directions for each type
of Cricut vinyl are available just by
googling Cricut and in the name of the
vinyl so right now I'm looking at Cricut
everyday I are not in cutting and
application instructions which I will
link in the description for this video
as well as in my tutorial over on my
blog alright so now we need to flip it
over and that's tricky of course because
this is a double-sided shirt right so
I'm going to turn it inside out and then
slip my cutting mat into the inside out
shirt and to press it down for another
25 to 30 seconds with my iron
all right so let's turn this right side
out and again we want to wait until the
carrier sheet is warm not hot and our
design is also warm not hot so you know
15 to 20 seconds approximately you'll
want to go by field just be careful of
your fingers when it looks good
go ahead and peel it off and there we go
that worked great looks good it feels
good awesome
and here's how it looks when it was all
done everything worked great so you can
use an iron or an EZ press it's really
up to you and what you want I prefer the
easy press because I don't have to guess
at the temperature or the time but an
iron also works all right so I'm gonna
do a bunch more so that you can see what
they look like this is a holographic
Sparkle which I thought was so pretty I
love this is got any one of my favorites
it was not difficult to weed or apply it
all isn't that just so pretty
definitely very pretty this is cricket
holographic sparkle iron on vinyl and
this is cricket mesh in red and I think
that it's mostly used for like jerseys
and such but it also I thought it was
really cute now this is cricket glitter
which I just adore how this looks and I
had no problems applying it or anything
like that
isn't that cute look at that look how
shiny that is it turned out great I love
the glitter and this is cricket foil in
rose gold I believe which is the same
exact color that I have on my apron and
I love this color combination this rose
gold in the turquoise oh this is so
pretty these different iron-on finishes
are just so much fun to play with okay
this might be my favorite I mean look at
that I love that it was even good enough
to transfer the Jennifer maker because
some of them weren't for you know the
the mesh one and the glitter one that
was much too fine and detail but
the the the foil when did great the
pattern one was not able to transfer
Jennifer make her but otherwise I had no
issues transferring its design to my
shirt and for an experiment I tried
putting sport flex on my cotton shirt
now this is not recommended sport flexes
for stretchy materials but I did it
anyways just to see what would happen
because some people try it I don't
recommend it it did work however I don't
know how well it's going to last but
just as an experiment I did it anyways I
love to test things so the foil of the
pattern and the sport flex now to take
care of your awesome new iron-on shirt
it's really important that you allow at
least 24 hours after you apply your
vinyl before you wash it and when you do
wash it turn it inside out and wash and
tumble dry and it's important that you
don't bleed chicks it'll mess with your
with your vinyl and it should last at
least 50 washes that is what cricket
says about their product and in my
experience that is very true I made a
t-shirt for my daughter a little under
two years ago it's been washed many
times and it still looks just as good as
when we first made it and it was my
first t-shirt then too so I think this
is a really good beginner project and
it's so much fun to make your own
t-shirts that are personalized and look
virtually as good as you might be able
to buy in a store now if you have
problems with your iron and vinyl and it
seems to pull away when you pull it your
carrier sheet it could mean a lot of
things the first thing it may mean is
that it's just a little bit too soon to
pull it away so stop and wait until it's
cooled off a little bit more you still
want to pull most vinyls not all but
most funnels that will that we do in
this tutorial are warm peel not cold
peel though not all you can check the
the cricket interactive guide tells you
whether it's a warm peel or cold peel
and I also
indicate that in my blog post about this
tutorial if that still doesn't work give
it some more heat so put that carrier
sheet back on and apply some more heat
with you know the same amount of
pressure and though that's typically the
only two things I've ever had to do to
fix any problems with the iron on vinyl
it's either I pulled it up too fast or
there just really wasn't enough heat now
one thing I want to know is that some
people say that it's really important
that you be able to see the fibers of
your shirt through your vinyl and that
by that I mean you can see the texture
of the shirt now I did a lot of testing
with specifically the Cricut everyday
iron-on which I think it was what most
people are going to be using and I found
that the only time that I could get the
fibers to show through the vinyl was
when I applied too much heat in other
words I did it two or three two or three
pressings which I know it's not accurate
and I did a little research and I don't
think that it's true that in every case
you want to see the fibers through your
vinyl you want to stick to you know see
the texture of it and in fact Cesar
which is an iron on vinyl company he
transformed I know company that knows
way more than I do about this they agree
with me they say that you don't always
have to see the texture of your fibers
through it for it to be applied
correctly so don't fall into the trap of
thinking that you have to see that what
I do notice however that with correctly
applied vinyl I can feel the texture so
it doesn't feel totally smooth I can
feel that the vinyl has melted into the
fabric of the shirt and it's you know
there's it feels very flat it doesn't
feel like it's going to want to peel off
when I run my hand over it and there's a
definite texture on the vinyl itself so
that's what I look for because we don't
want to over press our shirts and burn
our shirts or burn our vinyl because if
we have too much heat we can also
harm the adhesive and that could cause
it to peel after you wear it or wash it
so that's not the answer so just keep in
mind you don't you don't always have to
see the texture of the fibers through
your vinyl now this tutorial is a
covered a very basic and simple design
using variety of different iron-on
vinyls right but you might be wondering
can you combine and layer colors why yes
you can and you can put vinyl over
another layer of vinyl just so long as
you don't try to put anything over
glitter or glitter mesh or flocked vinyl
in fact it have a whole tutorial on
layering iron-on vinyl that you might
really enjoy if you're ready to take
your t-shirts to the next level if you
have any questions about making iron on
vinyl t-shirts please leave a comment
below or post over in my facebook group
at jennifer maker comm slash cricut
crafters and if you're curious about how
to make longer-lasting shirts using the
new cricut infusible inks i am getting a
whole box of invisible ink materials and
I'm gonna be making t-shirt tutorials
and all sorts of awesome things with you
I am so excited to do this and that's it
for today remember if you can tell me
what you want to make I could show you
how to make it until next time
[Music]
you